{"tossups": [{"question": "Qarlton Chelsted resigned his office in protest to the plans of a leader of one side in this conflict to burn his own capital. Lords Grandison, Cafferen, and Fell joined the eventual victor of this conflict after he defeated them at Summerhall. This conflict was ultimately caused by a knight naming someone other than his wife the \u201cqueen of love and beauty\u201d after winning a tournament and later locked her in the (*) Tower of Joy. Ser Willem Darry brought the child successors of the losing side in this conflict to Essos. This conflict\u2019s victor killed the enemy commander, Rhaegar, in single combat with his war hammer during the Battle of the Trident. For 10 points, name this conflict that toppled the House of Targaryen and placed the eldest son of Steffon Baratheon on the Iron Throne.", "answer": "Robert\u2019s Rebellion or the War of the Usurper (accept answers that suggest this is the conflict that makes Robert Baratheon king)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Robert\u2019s Rebellion or the War of the Usurper</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Robert\u2019s Rebellion or the War of the Usurper"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers that suggest this is the conflict that makes Robert Baratheon king"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s name has been translated as \u201ccity of the warm river\u201d, \u201cpalace illuminating the world of life\u201d, or a combination of the names of two tribes in Latin. The \u201cAndesite Sun\u201d was a giant sundial in this settlement. Archaeological evidence suggests that the chief priest of Zalmoxis was an influential figure in this city. The ruler who moved the capital to this city from Argedava supposedly gained power with the help of a wizard named Decaenus. In recent times, the most famous ruler of this city has had his face carved into a rock wall over the (*) Danube, and after his death, this city was destroyed in 106 CE. For 10 points, identify this city of Burebista and Decebalus, the Dacian capital destroyed by Trajan.", "answer": "Sarmizegetusa (accept answers that sound close, there are many variations on its name)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sarmizegetusa</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sarmizegetusa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers that sound close, there are many variations on its name"}, {"question": "A mass marriage of 1,000 couples was organized by Prince Yoto to reward men of merit joining this institution. Switching from one branch of this institution into a more prestigious one could be accompanied by the addition of the suffix \u201c-giya\u201d to one\u2019s surname. The ineffectiveness of this institution later in its history led to it being superseded by units called yong ying. This institution\u2019s first expansion doubled its numbers with the addition of (*) \u201cBordered\u201d groups that contrasted with the original \u201cPlain\u201d ones. This institution had separate branches for Mongols, Han Chinese, and Manchus and was begun under Nurhaci. For 10 points, what was this Qing institution that organized families into administrative and military groups?", "answer": "Banner system (accept Eight Banner armies, jak\u016bn g\u016bsa, or b\u0101q\u00ed; accept ethnic branches of the system; prompt on Manchu/Qing army)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Banner system</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Banner system"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Eight Banner armies, jak\u016bn g\u016bsa, or b\u0101q\u00ed; accept ethnic branches of the system; prompt on Manchu/Qing army"}, {"question": "The lawyer Gerry McGeer was influential in integrating this city into its country\u2019s rail system by arguing against high freight rates and he would later serve as mayor of this city. The first European to discover the location of this city was Jos\u00e9 Mar\u00eda Narv\u00e1ez in 1791. The \u201copen town\u201d policy of vice crime management instituted in the \u201830\u2019s in this city can still be seen in places like InSite where heroin addicts are given a safe place to shoot up. It\u2019s not San Francisco, but this city was also home to an (*) Asiatic Exclusion League, and it led a 1907 riot that ransacked its China- and Japantowns. This city has poorly handled the loss of the Stanley Cup to American teams, leading to riots in 1994 and 2011. For 10 points, identify this city on the Fraser River and primary port of western Canada.", "answer": "Vancouver", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Vancouver</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Vancouver"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Region and governing power required, e.g. \u201cSpanish America\u201d For most of the 19th century, this political region was governed from Bitola, the \u201ccity of consuls\u201d, and was a center for the 1903 Ilinden Revolt. This political region was policed by the martolos until the organization was merged with the pandor. The Banat Uprising occurred in a portion of this political region, for which the relics of St. Sava were burned in retaliation. The Pruth River Campaign restored this political region\u2019s northernmost major port, but the Treaty of (*) Kuchuk-Kainarji returned Azov to Russia. Perhaps the most famous attempt to leave this political region led to the formation of the League of Lezh\u00eb (\u201clezh-uh\u201d) and was led by the sanjakbey of Dibra, Skanderbeg. For 10 points, what is this political region brought under the rule of Istanbul by battles like Nicopolis and Kosovo and, despite two sieges, never included Vienna?", "answer": "Turkish Europe or Ottoman Europe (accept Rumelia or any answer that conveys Ottoman possessions in Europe as a whole; prompt on more specific areas, e.g. Serbia)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Turkish Europe or Ottoman Europe</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Turkish Europe or Ottoman Europe"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Rumelia or any answer that conveys Ottoman possessions in Europe as a whole; prompt on more specific areas, e.g. Serbia"}, {"question": "An administrator facing calls to respond to one of these events once said, \"Let the British public foot the bill for its 'cheap sentiment,'\u201d and only after that man left office was an official government plan instituted to combat these events. The Chalisa and Doji Bara events of this type occurred within 15 years of each other, the former emptying over half of the villages of the Doab. The government response to one of these events disastrously sought to avoid \u201cdependency\u201d, making refugees do heavy manual labor in return for (*) meager rations. The Japanese invasion of Burma stopped the region from exporting rice and sent thousands of refugees into India, exacerbating one of these events in Bengal in 1943. For 10 points, what are these catastrophic shortages of food?", "answer": "Indian famines", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Indian famines</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Indian famines"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One time barber, hydraulic engineer, priest, and circus strongman Giovanni Belzoni is best known for the removal of a statue from one of these places that is now in the British Museum. Some of these places had side structures called mammisi attached. Harkhuf\u2019s trading expedition was supported by these places that engaged in heku. The workers\u2019 village of Deir el-Medina was financed by a nearby group of these places. Reliefs describing the (*) Heb-Sed Festival are found on the Chappelle Rouge, a barque shrine at a famous one of these places. Rituals were performed at these places to ensure the administration of ma\u2019at by the gods. For 10 points, identify these places including the Ramesseum and Karnak where deities like Isis and Osiris were worshipped.", "answer": "Egyptian temples", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Egyptian temples</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Egyptian temples"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The name given to this people in many languages is semantically related to \u201cpale\u201d, suggesting that many were blonde; unsurprisingly, their women were very desirable among the Russian aristocracy. This people fought with Alexios I Komnenos in the Battle of Levounion against the Pechenegs. One person born of this ethnic group founded the first dynasty to rule the Delhi Sultanate. Ladislaus IV of Hungary bore an epithet reflecting his maternal ancestry from this people. (*) The Tale of Igor\u2019s Campaign tells of Igor Svyatoslavich of Novgorod\u2019s failed raid against this people. This people joined the Rus\u2019 to fight the Mongols at the Battle of the Kalka River. For 10 points, identify this Turkic people who most notably lived on the Pontic-Caspian steppe and formed a confederation with the Kipchaks.", "answer": "Cumans (prompt on Kipchaks before mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cumans</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cumans"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Kipchaks before mentioned"}, {"question": "Despite only separating in the 1830\u2019s, Oklahoma Cherokee has acquired these features while North Carolina Cherokee has not. Punjabi\u2019s loss of its voiced aspirates led it to develop these features and is the only Indo-European language to have done so. These features are affected by downdrift, which comes in discrete and terraced varieties. Meeussen\u2019s Rule describes restrictions on arranging these features in Bantu languages and is an example of the Obligatory (*) Contour Principle. Voiced consonants before vowels and word-final fricatives, respectively, can create low and high versions of these features on those vowels, and the largest concentrations of languages that employ these features phonemically are in West Africa and eastern Asia. For 10 points, what are these pitch-based phonemic features found in languages like Thai and Mandarin?", "answer": "tones", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>tones</u></b>", "acceptable": ["tones"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Tower of Elahbel in this city\u2019s Valley of the Tombs contained some of the earliest pieces of silk found in the Middle East. One story claims that the nephew of a leader of this city assassinated his uncle for reprimanding him for taking the first shot in a lion hunt. A ruler of this city claimed ancestry from Cleopatra and used this as justification for Septimius Zabdas\u2019 conquest of Egypt. This city was taken after defeats at Immae and Emesa, but was not sacked until after it rebelled against (*) Roman rule the following year. This city\u2019s most famous ruler served as regent for her son Vallabathus and shook off Roman rule on the advice of Cassius Longinus, but she was shortly thereafter brought to Rome in chains after being defeated by Emperor Aurelian. For 10 points, identify this Syrian city home to Zenobia.", "answer": "Palmyra (accept Tadmor or Tadmurta)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Palmyra</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Palmyra"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Tadmor or Tadmurta"}, {"question": "A bombing run in this battle was called \u201ca colossal blunder\u2026a piece of gross stupidity\u201d by Cardinal Secretary of State Luigi Maglione. Following this engagement, hundreds of civilian women from nearby villages were raped in an event called the Marocchinate. Polish forces in this battle included a private named Wojtek (\u201cvoy-tek\u201d), a Syrian brown bear, who carried ammunition, and that same unit was critical in taking a key mountaintop position in the final phase of this battle, called (*) Operation Diadem. Field Marshal Albert Kesselring declared to the Allies that his forces would not garrison a historic building during this battle. In the month following this battle, Lieutenant General Mark Clark captured nearby Rome. For 10 points, name this extended 1944 battle fought near a Benedictine monastery in central Italy.", "answer": "Battle of Monte Cassino", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Monte Cassino</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Monte Cassino"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A state in this modern country was supposedly founded by the twin sorcerers Olisihpa and Olosohpa who built an altar to the agriculture god Nahnisohn Sahpw with the help of a dragon. That state in this modern country was ruled from the city Nan Madol. The island of Kosrae (\u201ccoe-SHY\u201d) in this country contains the ruins of the city of Leluh and may have been the place from where Isokelekel launched his successful invasion of Pohnpei to overthrow the Saudeleur Dynasty. Truk Lagoon in this modern country was one of Japan\u2019s most important naval bases in WWII, and after the war, this country, along with (*) Palau and the Marshall Islands, was administered by the US until declaring independence in 1979. For 10 points, what is this modern country, which shares its name with a region of the Pacific north of Melanesia?", "answer": "Federated States of Micronesia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Federated States of Micronesia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Federated States of Micronesia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A chief of this tribe named Cameahwait rewarded the men who returned his sister and Otter Woman with horses. This tribe aided the US Army in fighting the Cheyenne and Lakota in the Battle of the Rosebud. The Bear River Massacre was perpetrated against members of this tribe. This tribe fought the Sheepeater War, which was the last Indian war in the (*) Pacific Northwest. An offshoot of this tribe would become the Comanche. A chief of this tribe is the namesake of Pocatello, Idaho. The most famous person of this tribe was captured by the Hidatsa before Toussaint Charbonneau took her as a wife. For 10 points, this is what tribe of Idaho and Wyoming to which Sacagawea belonged?", "answer": "Shoshone", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Shoshone</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Shoshone"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man gained the support of the Vlach settlers around Ioannina for his campaigns in northern Greece and Bulgaria. This leader was captured at the Battle of Melitene and held prisoner for three years by Danishmend Ghazi. This commander took the domain of his brother after defeating him at Fragneto. The Gesta Francorum was authored by an unknown scribe in the retinue of this man. The stories of this man\u2019s campaigns were so compelling that Henry I of England refused to allow this man into his kingdom out of fear of his vassals joining him in the (*) Holy Land. This general\u2019s most famous conquest was aided by the deception of the armorer Firouz. For 10 points, name this Norman leader of the First Crusade who established the Principality of Antioch.", "answer": "Bohemond I of Antioch (or Bohemond of Taranto)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Bohemond I of Antioch</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Bohemond I of Antioch"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Bohemond of Taranto"}, {"question": "In the 19th century, the \u201cmissionary to the world\u201d Joseph Wolff traveled throughout Asia in search of these people. Olaudah Equiano claimed that there was a \u201cstrong analogy which... appears to prevail in the manners and customs of my countrymen and those of\u201d these people. Brit-Am is an organization that seeks to prove the historical importance of these people. Nicholas McLeod\u2019s book Epitome of the Ancient History of Japan purports that the Japanese are descended from these people. The (*) Bnei Menashe people of NE India claim to be descended from these people. These people\u2019s characteristic status was gained upon being exiled by the Neo-Assyrians from their homeland in the Levant. For 10 points, identify this collection of ten groups of Jews who are believed by some to be the ancient progenitors of Jewish communities across the globe.", "answer": "Ten Lost Tribes of Israel (prompt on Jews)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ten Lost Tribes of Israel</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ten Lost Tribes of Israel"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Jews"}, {"question": "The losing commander in this battle supposedly cursed his countrymen who did not participate as recorded on the Gazimestan monument. The Knights Hospitaller participated in this battle under the leadership of John of Palisna. A letter to the Florentine government from Tvrtko I is one of the earliest sources on this battle. One side in this battle had been in decline since the reign Stefan Uro\u0161 V \u201cthe Weak\u201d. After this battle, the commander of the right flank of the winning side killed his brother Yakub, a competitor to his succession. The leader of one side in this battle was apocryphally assassinated when (*) Milo\u0161 Obili\u010d (\u201cmee-lohsh o-bee-leech\u201d) pretended to defect. For 10 points, name this 1389 Ottoman victory, which occurred at a site that names a disputed territory once part of Serbia.", "answer": "Battle of Kosovo Field", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Kosovo Field</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Kosovo Field"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a document to a fellow king, a ruler of this people, Burnaburiash I, relates that he was angry that that king did not know of and comfort him for his recent sickness, but forgave him once he learned that there was no way for that king to know because of how far away that ruler\u2019s kingdom was. This people erected kudurrus, which mark the boundaries of land grants from the king and contain curses on whoever disregards their authority. The first known reference to this people documents their failed campaign against Hammurabi\u2019s son Samsu-iluna. This people are most famous ruling from a city they called Karduniash, which they conquered in 1570 BCE, 25 years after the (*) Hittites had defeated its previous Amorite ruling dynasty. For 10 points, name this people, believed to have migrated from the Zagros Mountains, who controlled Babylon from the 16th-12th century BCE.", "answer": "Kassites (accept Galzu, Kashi, Kassi, or Ka\u0161\u0161u)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kassites</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kassites"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Galzu, Kashi, Kassi, or Ka\u0161\u0161u"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable  A prominent leader of this group was \u201cAnts the Terrible\u201d Kaljurand (\u201ckahl-you-rahnd\u201d). This group was countered by the istrebiteli who displayed executed members of this group in town squares. Along with the Cursed Soldiers, this group received aid from Operation Jungle. Members of this group tried to assassinate Vilis Lacis and many had received training as part of the Omakaitse. Operation Priboi, a large-scale deportation to Siberia, was largely done to weaken this insurgency. The goals of this paramilitary group were achieved by the organization (*) Saj\u016bdis (\u201csah-you-dees\u201d) and the Singing Revolution. For 10 points, what is this collective name for the insurgents resisting early Soviet rule in the Baltic States?", "answer": "Forest Brothers (or Forest Brethren or Brotherhood of the Forest or similar answers; accept descriptive answers that mention both the Baltic States and either the time period or that they fought the Soviets; prompt on partial descriptive answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Forest Brothers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Forest Brothers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Forest Brethren or Brotherhood of the Forest or similar answers; accept descriptive answers that mention both the Baltic States and either the time period or that they fought the Soviets; prompt on partial descriptive answers"}, {"question": "After being captured in battle, a warrior of this people had both of his hands chopped off, but upon being released, continued to fight with swords tied to his stumps. Hundreds of years of eastward migration and cultural influence put this people in the path of the Conquest of the Desert. The Zanja de Alsina was a trench built to protect against the malones, or raids, this people conducted against their neighbors. This people carried out the Destruction of the Seven Cities, eliminating foreign settlements south of the B\u00edo-B\u00edo river, and fought with the losing royalists in the (*) Guerra a muerte. Led in battle by toquis like Caupolic\u00e1n and Lautaro, this people is perhaps most famous for resisting Pedro de Valdivia. For 10 points, name these indigenous people of central Chile who successfully remained independent until the late 19th century", "answer": "Mapuche (prompt on Araucanians)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mapuche</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mapuche"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Araucanians"}, {"question": "At the age of 63, this man traveled the 90 miles between Forts Reno and Sill on horseback in 90 degree heat in one day to prove that he was still physically fit for military command. This man may have influenced the passage of the Pure Food and Drug Act with his denunciation of the \u201cembalmed beef\u201d provided to the army. As the final Commanding General of the United States Army, this man led the US invasion of (*) Puerto Rico and later became its first military governor. In one of the most famous actions under this man\u2019s command, Charles Gatewood negotiated for a group of Chiricahua Apache to be sent to a reservation in Florida. For 10 points, who was this man, a late 19th century American general, who was prominent in the Indian Wars and captured Chief Joseph and Geronimo?", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}